Guide to the William Goyen Papers, 1937-1978 MS 360
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Goyen to family, 1950-63; (233 items)
    - parents from New York, Dec. 22, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - mother from New York, Jan. 11, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Jan. 23, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 3, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 10, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - father from New York, Feb. 20, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 24, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 3, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 16, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 23, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, May 7, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - mother from New York, May 9, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from New York, May 19, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., May 26, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., June 4, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - father from Erwinna, Pa., June 11, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., June 18, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., June 27, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., July 7, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., July 29, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Aug. 11, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Aug. 25, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Sept. 3, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Sept. 30, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Oct. 27, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Nov. 6, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Nov. 24, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Jan. 3, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - mother from Erwinna, Pa., Jan. 3, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Feb. 4, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 9, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Feb. 14, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Telegram parents from New York, Feb. 22, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Mar. 3, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 10, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Mar. 17, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., Mar. 26, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., April 7, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., April 19, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., May 1, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., May 11, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., May 27, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., June 10, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., June 29, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., July 10, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Erwinna, Pa., July 15, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Aug. 11, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Sept. 7, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Oct. 5, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - father from Ottsville, Pa., Oct. 21, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - mother from Ottsville, Pa., Nov. __, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Nov. 16, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Dec. 3, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Jan. 7, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from New York, Jan. 22, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Mar. 29, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., Apr. 22, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - mother from Ottsville, Pa., May 7, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., May 21, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., June 8, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from Ottsville, Pa., June 27, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from New York, Oct. 3, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from New York, Oct. 18, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - mother from New York, Oct. 26, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - father from New York, Oct. 26, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from New York, Dec. 8, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from New York, Dec. 22, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - parents from New York, Jan. 3, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Jan. 12, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 4, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      describes fear/despair for career
    - parents from Boston, Mass., Mar. 10, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Apr. 1, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Apr. 11, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, June 7, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Telegram from Charles P. Goyen to Wm. Goyen, June 10, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, June 29, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, July 15, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Aug. 16, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Aug. 29, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Sept. 11, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Oct. 3, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Oct. 9, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Nov. 6, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Nov. 27, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      w/ 2 enclosures
    - parents from New York, Dec. 13, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - parents from New York, Jan. 7, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 5, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 5, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 19, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 31, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Apr. 10, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Apr. 30, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, May 14, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, May 30, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      w/ clipping on Goyen play
    - parents from New York, June 11, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, July 2, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from Fire Island, NY, July 11, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from Fire Island, NY, July 21, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - father from New York, Aug. 14, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Oct. 1, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from New York, Nov. 5, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      w/ ABC press release on show
    - parents from New York, Dec. 28, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - parents from Vevey, Switzerland, Jan. 3, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Berlin, W. Germany, Jan. 9, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Heidelburg, Jan. 20, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Cologne, Jan. 27, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Zurich, Feb. 4, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Zurich, Feb. 25, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Zurich, Mar. 15, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Zurich, Apr. 14, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Zurich, Apr. 17, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from Zurich, Apr. 20, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      enclosure: ACS to mother
    - parents from Kiel, Germany, May 19, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      dislikes teaching at Kiel U.
    - parents from Hansburg, May 26, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, June 6, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, June 10, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, June 24, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, July 4, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, July 24, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Aug. 19, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Sept. 7, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Oct. 2, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Nov. 2, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Nov. 17, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Dec. 7, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Dec. 20, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Dec. 29, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - parents from New York, Jan. 13, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, Feb. 3, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, Mar. 31, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, Apr. 14, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, Apr. 28, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, May 26, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, June 13, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - parents from New York, July 2 and 9, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Family ephemera (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Scope and Contents note
    includes newspaper clippings; 2 copies of The Cougar (2/6/42 and 12/11/42); church bulletins; graduation exercises; program for US Naval Reserve Midshipmen's School; USS Casablanca menus; greeting cards sent to Goyen family; etc.
- Series II: Works by Goyen
  - The House of Breath
    - Goyen bibliography (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 4 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 5 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 6 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Chapter 7 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 8 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 9 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 10 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 11 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 12 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 13 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Misc. manuscript pages (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Glaucus, and Four American Portraits
    - Early versions (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Notes (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Early Draft, (65 pp) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - (2nd?) Draft, (180 pp) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - (3rd?) Draft, (181 pp) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Uncorrected Proof (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Ghost and Flesh
    - Notes (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Notes (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The White Rooster, notes, etc. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Nests in a Stone Image, notes, etc. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Old Somebody's Children, notes, etc. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - A Shape of Light, notes, etc. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Letter in the Cedar Chest, notes, etc. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Kite, notes, etc. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Ghost and Flesh, Revisions and drafts (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Ghost and Flesh, Drafts (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Ghost and Flesh, Draft (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Ghost and Flesh, Uncorrected proof (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - In a Farther Country
    - Notes, handwritten passages, etc. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Notes, revisions (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Drafts (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Final draft (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The Faces of Blood Kindred
    - Story (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Old Wildwood (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - The Moss Rose (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - The Armadillo Basket (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Rhody's Path (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - A People of Grass (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - A Tale of Inheritance/ Zamour (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - The Geranium (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - The Horse and the Dry Moth (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Faces of Blood Kindred, Manuscript and printer's notes (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Faces of Blood Kindred, Galleys (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Faces of Blood Kindred, Page Proofs (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Half a Look of Cain, typescript, MS handwritten (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - The Fair Sister
    - Savata, My Fair Sister (Original story -- annotated by Goyen (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Typescript (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Carbon of typescript (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Galleys (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Page proofs (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - also: 1 copy of The Fair Sister (Box 10)
- Series III: Serial Publications
  - The Children, in Writings from the Rice Institute, Feb. 11, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The White Rooster, in Mademoiselle, April 1947 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Evil, in The Illiterati, No. 5, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Four American Portraits as Elegy, in Accent, Spring 1948 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The White Rooster, in Horizon, March 1949 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Fallen Splendid House, in Southwest Review, Spring 1949 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Wind in the Shutter, in Southwest Review, Summer 1949 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - A Bridge of Breath, in Partisan Review, June 1949 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Her Breath upon the Windowpane, in Harper's, July 1950 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Storm Doll, in Harper's Bazaar, October 1950 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Christy, in Southwest Review, Winter 1950 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Ghost of Raymond Emmons, in Mademoiselle, February 1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Children of Old Somebody, in Southwest Review, Summer 1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Pore Perrie, in Mademoiselle, July 1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - A Shape of Light, in Southwest Review, Winter 1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The People of Joseph Glasco, January 1953 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    program for art exhibition
  - The Enchanted Nurse, in Southwest Review, Summer 1953 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Armadillo Basket, in Harper's Magazine, December 1953 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Figure over the Town, in Bottigha Oscure, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Geranium, in Mademoiselle, April 1954 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - A People of Grass, in Bottigha Oscure, Spring 1956 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Small Talk on the Way to Damnation, in New York Times Book Review, Nov. 1956 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    (Book review of Brothers and Sisters by Ivy Compton-Burnett)
  - Review of The Grass Harp by Truman Capote (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Le Gaucher by Arthur Penn, Ballade de William Goyen (Paroles), Novembre 1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Vieux Bois Sauvage in La Nouvelle Revue Francaise, (Translated by Patrice Repusseau), Janvier 1977 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - While you were away, April 24, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    A talk delivered by Wm. Goyen at Houston Public Library
  - Delta # 9: William Goyen (Box 11, Folder 4)
    (includes interviews w/ Goyen, Goyen correspondence, unpublished pieces, and articles relating to WG and his writings)
  - Poetry: angoisse, autour du lac, icare aux champs (Box 11, Folder 4)
    also:
  - The figure over the town, in Saturday Evening Post, April 27, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - After the Fall of the Dream in Show, Sept. 1964 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    (article)
  - Country Folks Paved the Way to the Alley, in Texas Sunday Magazine, Nov. 24, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - A Parable of Perez, in New Directions, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Reviews and publicity
  - The House of Breath, (17 items) (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - The Fair Sister, (9 items) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Come, the Restorer; Selected Writings of WG, (8 items) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Other works, (8 items) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Interviews, (3 items) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Publicity relating to Rice University (includes Sallyport articles, etc., newspaper clippings, correspondence regarding Goyen's honorary degree, 2 photos of Goyen in academic regalia), (13 items) (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Houston Public Library exhibit and misc. items, (14 items) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - The House of Breath (play), (5 items) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - World within World, The Autobiography of Stephen Spender, 1951 (Box 12)
    (acknowledges Goyen)
  - The Lazy Ones, by Albert Cossery. Trans. by Wm. Goyen (Box 12)
  - The Glass House, The Life of Theodore Roethke, by Allen Seager (Box 12)
    (partially edited by Goyen?)
  - Tape: Interview between William Goyen (1977 Distinguished Alum. Award) and Steve Barnhill, David Rodwell, Rob Wilds, May 13, 1977 (Box 12)
  - An Approach to William Goyen's The House of Breath, [UNK] Arts Dissertation by Patrice [UNK] (Paris, 1971) (Box 12)
  - Mid-American Review, 1992 (Box 12)
- Series V: Proofs and Galleys (Box 13)
  - The Collected Stories of William Goyen - uncorrected proof (Box 13)
  - The Collected Stories of William Goyen - printer's set of galleys (Box 13)
  - Precious Door, proof sheets (Box 13)
  - Nine Poems, page proofs (Box 13)
  - A Book of Jesus
    - Two sets of printer's galleys (Box 13)
    - Publisher's dummy (Box 13)